Guide to Tuli Kupferberg and Sylvia Topp Papers MSS.385
Fales Library and Special Collections
Tuli Kupferberg and Sylvia Topp Papers
1821-2010
1960-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
Kupferberg, Samara
Kupferberg, Tuli
Topp, Sylvia
MSS.385
202.75 Linear Feet in 106 record cartons, 146 manuscript boxes, 1 half-manuscript box, 1 tall manuscript box, 30 flat boxes, 3 hinged-ring binder boxes, 33 oversize flat boxes, 4 flat-file folders, 1 suitcase, 2 musical instruments, 1 toy gun
3 sound discs (vinyl)
2 sound discs (cd)
2 dvd-r disks
86 sound tape reels
273 audiocassettes
2 sound cassettes (dat)
33 videocassettes (minidv)
3 film reels
132 videocassettes (vhs)
16 videocassettes (u-matic)
1 videoreels (1 inch)
Naphtali "Tuli" Kupferberg (1923-2010) was an American counterculture poet, cartoonist, publisher, activist, and musician. This collection reflects the varied, interconnected assortment of projects Kupferberg undertook beginning in the 1940s until his death in 2010, while living in lower Manhattan. Material in this collection includes essays, articles, and books by Kupferberg and his wife Sylvia Topp; work files for his and Topp's publishing company, Birth Press; fan mail, song lyrics, and recordings related to his band, The Fugs; props for his performance group, The Revolting Theater; and recordings of his local television show, Revolting News. His correspondence with authors including Sparrow, Urban Gwerder, Ted Joans, Walter Lowenfels, and Coby Batty, provide perspective into the network and relationships among the literary bohemian community within New York and beyond during the 1960s through 2000s. The bulk of the collection is Kupferberg's extensive research and source material grouped into subjects including sex, politics, smoking, religion, drugs, and education. Material within these subject files were used as inspiration or incorporated into works he wrote and performed. His significant collection of local, small-run independent published material as well as mainstream publications illustrates the output of writers and artists during these decades, and represents the interests of readers within the New York community and beyond.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in nine series, one of which has been further arranged into two subseries.
The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I. Writings
Series II. Cartoons/Collages
Series III. The Fugs
Series IV. Projects
Series V. Birth Press
Series VI. Research and Source Material
Subseries A. Research and Subject files
Subseries B. Source Publications
Series VII. Publications
Series VIII. Correspondence
Series IX. Performance Props and Costumes
Biographical Note
Naphtali "Tuli" Kupferberg (1923-2010) was an American counterculture poet, publisher, performance artist, cartoonist, activist, and founding member of the underground rock band, The Fugs.
He grew up in Manhattan and attended Brooklyn College, graduating in 1944. Before graduating from college, Kupferberg had already become active in the literary and political scenes in downtown New York City, publishing poems, short stories, and essays in local journals and newspapers, including the The Village Voice, Midstream, and Liberation. He also drew cartoons and collages beginning in the 1950s, his earliest work including drawings with captions of witty, altered aphorisms, which were accepted in a number of publications and in book form.
Throughout his life, Kupferberg was also known for being politically active, participating in protests and rallies; during his appearances with his band The Fugs; his published articles, as well as co-authoring a satirical anti-war book 1001 Ways to Beat the Draft (1966) with Robert Bashlow.
Kupferberg met Sylvia Topp (1935- ) in 1957 and were together until his death in 2010. Initially, they lived together in the East Village, starting a publishing company, Birth Press (also known as Vanity Press) in the late 1950s, working out of their apartment. They published not only Kupferberg's works, but other authors of this period as well. Between 1958 and 1965 they released a number of publications from the Birth Press imprint, including the zines Birth, Yeah, and Swing, as well as the collage-and-quotation-assemblages 1001 Ways to Live Without Working; Beatniks: or, The War Against the Beats; The Rub-ya-out of Omore Diem; The Christine Keeler Colouring Book & Cautionary Tale; The Mississippi (A Study of the White Race); and Children As Authors: A Big Bibliography. Topp and Kupferberg also edited a number of mainstream reference books, including As They Were, As They Were Too, and First Glance: Childhood Creations of the Famous.
Simultaneously his cartoons and articles were also being accepted in publications like The Soho Weekly News, The Village Voice, and High Times. Throughout this time, Topp worked as a freelance copy editor for various publishing houses, including Grove Press and Academic Press, which also published Kupferberg's material.
Kupferberg was also involved in the New York music scene, becoming a founding member of the rock band, The Fugs, in 1964 with poet Ed Sanders and Ken Weaver. The Fugs performed in galleries, clubs, and theaters throughout New York; recorded six albums; and toured regularly. The Fugs' involvement in counter cultural politics and the anti-war movement enabled Kupferberg to be present at a number of seminal events, including the 1967 March on Washington and 1968 Chicago Democratic Convention.
During the early 1970s, while on a break from The Fugs, Kupferberg, along with Sylvia Topp, formed a satirical experimental theatrical group called the Revolting Theater. The material originated from Kupferberg's 1966 solo album, No Deposit, No Return.
Kupferberg also appeared as an actor in a number of movies: W.R.: Mysteries of the Organism (1971) depicting the life and work of Wilhelm Reich; Kupferberg and Revolting Theater members performed a sketch in the Richard Pryor film Dynamite Chicken (1972); and he starred in the Canadian experimental feature film Voulez-Vous Coucher Avec God? (1972).
Kupferberg began writing what he described as "parasongs" in the 1970s, which consisted of new lyrics adapted to known melodies. Many were published in his 1973 book, Listen to the Mockingbird, which had multiple editions over the next 20 years.
In 1989 Kupferberg became involved with television, producing a show with Lannes Kenfield, Theater of the Real. They went on to make the show, Revolting News, broadcast on a local New York City community channel starting in 1992, on which he delivered satirical "newspoems" and "perverbs," and discussed a variety of topics, including Judaism, sexuality, spiritualism, and militarism.
Throughout the 1990s, Kupferberg sold cartoons, books, and records from a table on the sidewalk of Spring Street near his New York apartment. Until his death in 2010, he videotaped and posted online readings and performances of his works, as well as continued to draw and write, with many regularly published in newspapers and magazines.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Some material in the collection is presently too delicate for researchers to handle. See individual object entries for details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Sylvia Topp and Samara Kupferberg in 2013. The accession numbers associated with this purchase are 2013.385 and 2014.385.
Related Materials
Additional material can be found in the following archival collections:
Tuli Kupferberg Radical Humor Collection (TAM 422) located in the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Fugs Archives (MSS 013) located in the Fales Library & Special Collections.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of over 60 years of material generated by Tuli Kupferberg through his writings; music lyrics; cartoons and collages; sound and video recordings; performance props; and publications. His work was often inspired by political and social issues, including protesting Vietnam War in music lyrics and cartoons, criticizing a Presidential administration in Birth Press publications and his Revolting News television show, and discussing the drug culture in his Dope Lore magazine columns. Kupferberg corresponded with many writers and poets active in the 1960s, 70s, and 80s, which provides a view into the literary community during these decades, including Sparrow, Urban Gwerder, Ted Joans, Walter Lowenfels, and Coby Batty. These correspondents discussed submissions to Kupferberg and Topp's Birth Press publications, shared their own publications, and updated Kupferberg on news of their families as well as mutual friends.
The Fugs material in this collection illustrates the development of a band active in the 1960s through promotional advertisements, flyers, and set lists, performing primarily in local New York area clubs. The band's popularity spread beyond the bohemian and hippie population of the New York area and expanded throughout the United States as well as internationally, illustrated through concert tour planning files and fan mail addressed to both Kupferberg and band co-founder Ed Sanders. Their music was initially focused on protesting against the Vietnam War, but eventually evolved into general political satire, which can be traced through their set lists and published/unpublished recordings found in this collection.
A significant portion of this collection is Kupferberg's extensive research and source material accumulated throughout his life and grouped into subject headings such as humor, sex, religion, education, war, and politics. These files contained clippings, articles, print advertisements, illustrations, photographs, and political cartoons, ranging in date from the late 1800s to 2010. These files were used by Kupferberg in his collages and publications, but also as visual elements in performances with The Fugs, Revolting Theater, and his solo act, many helping to convey his satirical interpretations on politics, sex, war, and drug use. Along with these source files, his collection of small-run publications represents the literary and artistic output of lower Manhattan writers and artists from the 1950s to the mid-2000s, while his collection of wider-circulated publications provide a broader view of popular culture nationally and internationally during the same time period.
Separated Materials
All Birth Press books, magazines, and booklets were separated from this collection and cataloged separately.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Appraisal
Publications with existing issues within Bobst Library, as well as props in poor condition were deaccessioned.
Two computer disks were imaged. No information was recovered off of the one disk and the second contained only an article not related to Kupferberg.
Announcements.; Beat generation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bohemianism -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Costume.; Fliers (printed matter); Manuscripts for publication.; Masks.; Performance art.; Political ballads and songs -- United States.; Political cartoons -- United States.; Political satire, American.; Props (object genres); Protest poetry.; Serial publications.; Wit and humor, Pictorial; Kupferberg, Samara; Topp, Sylvia; Batty, Coby; Birth Press; Fugs (Musical group); Gwerder, Urban, 1944-; Joans, Ted; Lowenfels, Walter, 1897-1976.; Sanders, Ed; Sparrow, (American poet)
- Series I. Writings, 1833, 1851-1907, 1930-2010, undated; 31.44 Linear Feet in 24 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, 6 flat boxes; 1.4 Megabytes
  Arrangement
  Folders are arranged in the original order of the donor: alphabetical by the writing's title or subject. Some of these files were alphabetized by a definite/indefinite article, and sometimes following the article (ie. the, a). Folders for Listen to the Mockingbird are grouped by edition (there were five) and alphabetically within each edition. The poem and newspoem files were left as originally filed by the donor, with the majority of the poems grouped under letters of the alphabet, rather than individual titles. Only a small group of the poem files were listed by individual titles. The newspoem files were also left in their original order, with minimal desciption of individual works. Kupferberg's collection of notecards, notebooks, and scrapbooks come at the end of the series inventory after the writings files.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains working files related to published and unpublished writings by Kupferberg, dating from the early 1940s to the early 2000s. Materials in this series provide a glimpse into Kupferberg's creative process and working style through his manuscripts, typescripts, notes, outlines, electronic records, and source material. His early works from the 1940s and 1950s include college coursework papers and early publication submissions, many using variations on his name, including Norman Kupferberg, Naftali Kupferberg, Norman Cooper, Arab Kupa, and Tuli Kupferberg. Of note is an unpublished manuscript from the 1940s, The Novel, which is believed to be an autobiographical account of Kupferberg's teen and college years. Scrapbooks within this series contain clippings of some of his early published writings. Kupferberg often self-published through his company, Birth Press, including his popular parody song lyric book, Listen to the Mockingbird, (1973) of which this series includes his illustrations, drafts, and source material for all five editions. This series also contains images, notes, and reviews for the books As They Were (1973) and As They Were Too (1979), which were in collaboration with Sylvia Topp. Chapter outlines and drafts for his unpublished novel The Fucks (inspired by Kupferberg's band The Fugs) can also be found in this series. He also wrote for many underground and mainstream publications, including a column, Dope Lore, for High Times magazine, of which this series contains source material, and reader letters. A large collection of notes, drafts, and source material related to Kupferberg's poems and newspoems, which were poems inspired by news clippings, can be found in this series, ranging in date from the 1940s to the early 2000s. Kupferberg often accumulated research information for his writings on notecards, and this series contains cards for 1001 Ways to Make Love and notes for First Glance: Childhood Creations of the Famous, as well as ideas for Dope Lore. Small notebooks kept throughout his life in which he recording writing ideas, quotes, and general thoughts can also be found in this series. Material specifically related to Kupferberg's Birth Press publications can also be found in Series V.
  - 5 Little Tales of Terror, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 21 Gun Salutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 21 Things to Be Thankful For (Thanksgiving), 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 76 Reasons, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 101 Advices From Authors (For SoHo Weekly News), undated (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - 101 Economic Epigrams, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 101 New York Cheers and Jeers, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 37, Folder 1)
  - 101 Sexist Sayings, 1972, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 339 Lists About God, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1001 Ways to Make Love, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1001 Ways to ? Revolution - Bashlow Notes, Letters, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 3000 Ways…, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 200,000,000 Guns & the Presidents Who Brought Us There, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A Letter to Bakunin to His Brother Paul, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - A Letter to My Brothers and Sisters, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - A Little Anthology of Sad Poetry, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - A Salute (21-Gun) to Journalism, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - A Sermon and a Song (Copy of Talk at Irving Plaza), 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - A Simple Solution to the White Problem, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - A Simple Statement on the War, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Adventures of Super Cock (Performance Skit?), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - After the Balls Are Ova, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Al's Flight Einstein: The World as I See It, circa 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Alex and McGuffy, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - All the World Loves a Loser: Great Mistakes, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Allotment, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - America Goes to Hell, circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Horse Apples, circa 2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - An Analysis of Human Life, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Anarchism Among the Jews (Book Review), circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Aphorisms - A Sampling, 1977-2010 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Aphorisms - Labor-related, Bicentennial, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - April Fools (Articles), 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Are the Police Necessary?, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Are These Our Children?, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 36-40)
  - Art and Politics, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Art and Politics - Revolting Art (Book), 1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 42-43)
  - Art is Death, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - As They Were, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 45-50, Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - As They Were / First Glance - Images, circa 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - As They Were / As They Were Too - Images, circa 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
  - As They Were Too, 1972-1979 (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
  - As They Were Too - Images, Research, 1982-1993 (Box 51, Folder 1-3)
  - The Asexual Handbook, circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Ask Dr. Fuck (Column), 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
  - At a Glance [aka First Glance] - Alphabetical Research Files, 1970-1977 (Box 22, Folder 6-17, Box 51, Folder 4-46)
  - Baddy - Wad Words (Curse Words of All Nations), 1970-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-27, Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Be My Comic Valentine, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3-8)
  - Beat Prose, 1940s, 1959, 1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Beat the Reaper, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Beating, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Beginning Woe Losers, 1965-1966, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Best Rests (Satirical Restaurant Review), undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Biographies for writers Rolf-Ulrich, Kaiser, Sanders, Ginsberg, Mekas, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Birds Do It (Article), 1980s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Blab of the Pave, 1979-2010 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - A Black and White Manifesto: Thoughts on the White Problem, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The (Body) Parts Left Out of the Contragate Hearings, 1987-2010 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - The Book of Perverbs, 1975-1983, 2002-2007, undated (Box 3, Folder 19-20, Box 51, Folder 47-49)
  - The Book of the Body - Excerpts, circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Book and Play Reviews, 1948-1952, 1968, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Book Review - Reich's Journals, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn College (Speech?), undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Caca Caper, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Call Me Adam - or My Life With a Beard, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Caption for East Village Other Slum God (Photograph of Kupferberg), undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Carpe Diem: Seize the Day, 1977-1991 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - Caught in the Act: A Legal Vaudeville, 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The Child's Inquiry, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Colin's Funeral Benefit, circa 2000s (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - College Class Papers and Notes, 1942-1949 (Box 3, Folder 34-46)
  - Columbus, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Columbus, for 500th Anniversary, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Concentration Camp Follies of 1969 (Play / Movie Script), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Coveners of the Dream - Ode to 1984 Democratic Convention, circa 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cost of Living, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Crumb Brothers Almanac, 1976-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Dave McReynolds Dinner, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Democracy in America - AHA #2, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - De Natura, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Department Store (Play), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - A Diatribe with Myself ABT Not-Violence, circa 1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Die Laughing, 1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 13-16, Box 51, Folder 50)
  - Don't Cut It Off: In Praise of the Foreskin (Article) By Sylvia Topp Re: Circumcision, undated (Box 4, Folder 17, Box 51, Folder 51)
  - Don't Make Trouble, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 18-22)
  - Dope Lore (Column for High Times Magazine), 1851, 1851-1907, 1930-1938, 1970-1988 (Box 4, Folder 23-37, Box 5, Folder 1-10, Box 51, Folder 52-57)
  - Dover Beach, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The Dragon, circa 2000 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Driver, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Dumb Records, 1973-1990 (Box 5, Folder 14, Box 52, Folder 1-8)
  - Dumb Records, Pyrrhic Victories / Worst of Everything, 1975-1984 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Ethnic Slurs - From Worst of Everything, 1960-1981 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
  - Epitaphs: A Sampling, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Fabulous Flops, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Farts from the Bowels of the Monster, 1970-1986 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Fear of Violence, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - First Glance - Correspondence, Credits, Chapter Layouts, etc., 1970-1985 (Box 5, Folder 22-46, Box 6, Folder 1-72, Box 7, Folder 1-41)
  - Five Star Finale, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - The Free Union, circa 1947 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - From Under the World, undated (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Fuck Nam: A Morality Play, circa 1966 (Box 7, Folder 45-47)
  - Fucklore (Column), 1963-1983 (Box 7, Folder 48-49, Box 52, Folder 9-10)
  - The Fucks (Novel), circa 1970s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 50-60, Box 8, Folder 1-8)
  - The Fugs, 2005 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - The Function of Bohemia, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Gallego, Etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Get Kancer!, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - The Ghouls at Night (Play), undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Give War a Chance, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - God Bless the Child, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - God is on Our Side, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Going to the Demo - Contraception, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - The Grace and Beauty of the Human Form, 1833, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 18, Box 52, Folder 11)
  - Graffiti Cartoon, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Great Graffiti, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 20-23)
  - Great Quotations from the Presidents, circa 1979 (Box 8, Folder 24-25)
  - Growing Up Jewish, 1998-2004 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - The H-Bomb's Thunder, 1972-1988 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Handwritten Notes, Etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Harvard Dropouts, 1994, undated (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Hey Sport!, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Hip and Square, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - How Shall I Put It?, 1975-1983 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - How Shall We Survive?, circa 1963-1969 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - How to Spend Yourself, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - The Hustlers (Play), circa 1950s (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - I'm a Nervous Wreck from Georgia Tech, 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - I'm Glad I Didn't Say That, 1961, 1973-1997 (Box 8, Folder 37-39, Box 52, Folder 12-16)
  - I'm in Love with an Installation, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - I'm Muscle Bound, undated (Box 8, Folder 41)